Byzantine Institute, Inc. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection. The Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks Fieldwork Records and Papers, ca. late 1920s-2000s: Finding Aid
Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives, Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection
- Administrative Records, 1920s - 2000s, MS.BZ.004-01; 28 boxes including 333 folders
  - Correspondence, ca. 1920s - 2000s, MS.BZ.004-01-01; 20 boxes including 280 folders
    - Correspondence, ca. 1950s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04; 8 boxes including 122 folders
      - Correspondence between the Fogg Art Museum (e.g., Edward Forbes), Dumbarton Oaks (e.g., John Thacher), and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., William MacDonald), January 1953 – September 1957Bulk: January 1953 - January 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-126; 1 folder
        Relates to donations and funding for the Byzantine Institute
        Fogg Art Museum, 1895-
      - Correspondence between the Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, March 1953 – February 1961, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-127; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between Paul Underwood and John Thacher, April – December 1953, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-128; 1 folder
        Includes reports on the progress of the work in Istanbul, financial statements, and personal matters
      - Correspondence between the Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, April 1953 – August 1966Bulk: April 1953 - August 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-129; 1 folder
        Includes letters about the possible expansion of archaeological activities in Istanbul and the work on the bronze doors in Hagia Sophia
      - Correspondence between Oxford University Press and Thelma Hammack, April 1953 – November 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-130; 1 folder
        Thelma Hammack was a staff member at Dumbarton Oaks beginning in 1953.
        Hammack, Thelma
      - Correspondence between Elias Lavriotes of Holy Monastery of the Grand Lavra and John Thacher, April 1953 – February 1964Bulk: April 1953 - July 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-131; 1 folder
        Correspondence following Thacher's visit to Mount Athos in 1953. Thacher sends some goods and financial support, including funds for the restoration of the church of Saint John under the jurisdiction of the Monastery of Koutloumous. In return, Elias Lavriotes sends him objects, e.g. wood-carved items.
        Elias Lavriotes was a monk at the Holy Monastery of Grand Lavra, Mt. Athos, Chalcidiki, Greece
        Lavriotes, Elias
      - Correspondence with John Thacher, Bulk: February 1965 - November 1967April 1953 – June 1968, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-132; 1 folder
        Includes a proposal to renovate the Monastery of Chilandari at Mount Athos
      - Correspondence between Greek Orthodox Diocese of North and South America and John Thacher, June 1953 – April 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-133; 1 folder
        Includes an account on riots and the destruction of Greek churches, schools and cemeteries in Istanbul; booklets with information on the Orthodox and other Eastern churches in North America; and postcards from Mount Athos
        Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America, 1921-
      - Correspondence between Greek Orthodox organizations and John Thacher, July 1953 – November 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-134; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Lawrence Majewski, John Thacher, and Alberta Carpenter), July 1953 – May 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-135/136; 2 folders; *"Lawrence" or "Laurence"
        Relates to finances and projects related to Kariye Camii
        Majewski, Lawrence J., 1919-1999
      - Correspondence between Fritz Bilfinger and John Thacher, August 1953 – April 1965, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-137; 1 folder
        Relates to scaffolding at Hagia Sophia
        Fritz Bilfinger was possibly Red Cross delegate
        Bilfinger, Fritz
      - Correspondence between Turkish students and John Thacher, October 1953 – March 1964Bulk: October 1953 - July 1956, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-138; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between Ernest Hawkins and John Thacher, December 1953 – December 1957, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-139/140; 2 folders
        Relates to Hawkins’s finances and fieldwork projects in Cyprus and Turkey
      - Correspondence between John Dane Jr. and John Thacher, December 1953 - August 1963, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-141; 1 folder
        Relates to changes in the Byzantine Institute's Board of Directors and new letterheads; scaffolding problems; fund raising; and meeting minutes
        John Dane, Jr. was a lawyer with Choate, Hall and Stewart in Boston, Massachusetts, ca. 1950s
        Dane, John Jr.
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, Bulk: 1958-1960December 1953 - November 1966, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-142; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between Ercüment Atabay and John Thacher, Bulk: January 1958 - September 19631953 - 1965, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-143; 1 folder
        Includes correspondence with Byzantine Institute fund contributors and photograph requests concerning the frescoes in Kariye Camii
        Ercüment Atabay was a professor of humanities at Robert College and Bogazici University. In the 1940s and 1950s, he assisted Robert Van Nice in his survey work at Hagia Sophia, recording approximately 1500 mason's marks from the building. He also assisted Paul Underwood while Underwood was field director of the Byzantine Institute.
        Atabay, Ercüment, 1922-
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, January - February 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-144; 1 folder
        Relates to the "fake wooden dome" at Kariye Camii, the St. Irene project, and a report for the southwest room in Hagia Sophia
        Related materials regarding the St. Irene project are available in Subgroup I, Box 2.
      - Permit from the Ministry of Education in Turkey for work at Zeyrek Camii and letter from the Istanbul Directorship of Foundations to the Byzantine Institute, February 1954-March 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-145; 1 folder
        Letter from the Istanbul Directorship of Foundations relates to a proposal to repair the mosque of Hirami Ahmet Pasa Camii
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, March 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-146; 1 folder
        Relates to the publication of materials from Kariye Camii
      - Correspondence with John Thacher, March 1954 - August 1966Bulk: March 1954 - September 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-147; 1 folder
        Includes a letter from Thacher to Fletcher Warren, the U.S. Ambassador in Turkey, introducing Lawrence Majewski as the Deputy Field Director of the Byzantine Institute
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, April - October 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-148; 1 folder
        Relates to new workers on the projects in Istanbul; financial matters, and meeting minutes
      - Correspondence between the Houston Friends of the Byzantine Institute and John Thacher, April 1954 - December 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-149; 1 folder
        Houston Friends of the Byzantine Institute was a group of individuals in Houston, Texas, who conducted fundraising campaigns for the Byzantine Institute
        Houston Friends of the Byzantine Institute
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, April 1954 - December 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-150; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, May 1954 - April 1962, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-151; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between Paul Fekula and John Thacher, August - September 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-152; 1 folder
        Includes the article "Icon-Mosaics of Kahrie-Djami" by Paul Fekula
        Paul Fekula was a collector of Russian manuscripts
        Fekula, Paul, 1905-1982
      - Correspondence between The Metropolitan of Philadelphia and John Thacher, August 1954 - July 1965, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-153; 1 folder
        Includes information on the situation of the Ecumenical Patriarchate
        James, Metropolitan of Philadelphia, Ecumenical Patriarchate, Istanbul was an acquaintance of John Thacher.
        James, Metropolitan of Philadelphia
      - Correspondence between the Greek Archdiocese of North and South America and John Thacher, September - October 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-154; 1 folder
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-155; 1 folder
        Includes work reports from Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, 1954, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-156; 1 folder
        The correspondence on October 19, 1954 states: “P.S. It might interest you to know that the Boston office of the Institute is no more. Therefore whatever Institute matters not handled here at Dumbarton Oaks will be taken care of in Mr. Brown’s office in Providence. Bill McDonald is in Rome.”
      - Work permits for Zeyrek Mosque, 1954 -1957, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-157; 1 folder
        Includes a Turkish article discussing the state of the Zeyrek Mosque
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, January - March 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-158; 1 folder
        Includes: a newspaper article from the Houston Chronicle Rotogravure Magazine from July 3, 1955, “A hand from Houston helps restore Byzantine art;” financial statements; photograph requests; meeting minutes; inquiries for public lectures; and a draft for a newspaper article
      - Correspondence with John Thacher, Hubbert R. Quinter, and George B. Quatman, January 1955 - November 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-159; 1 folder
        Quinter, Hubbert R.
        Quatman, George B.
      - Correspondence between Ethel André de Limur and John Thacher, March 1955 - April 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-160; 1 folder
        Relates to financial contributions
        Ethel de Limur was a supporter of the Byzantine Institute and spouse of French count and diplomat Andre de Limur
        de Limur, Ethel
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, April 1955 - June 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-161; 1 folder
        Relates to the publication of preliminary reports on Kariye Camii, photographic material and use of ultra-violet light; and meeting minutes
      - Correspondence between Madame L. Mamboury and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., John Thacher and Paul Underwood), April 1955-July 1956, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-162; 1 folder
        Relates to the purchase of the Mamboury library by the Byzantine Institute
        Léonie Mamboury, spouse of Ernest Mamboury, sold her husband's library to the Byzantine Institute Library in 1956.
        Mamboury, Léonie
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, April 1955 - October 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-163; 1 folder
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, July - December 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-164; 1 folder
        Relates to a draft for “Descente aux Limbes (Anastasis);” publication of the preliminary reports on Kariye Camii; publicity for the work in Istanbul through newspaper articles, photographs, and postcards; and the new director of the Hagia Sophia Museum
      - Correspondence with Ernst Kitzinger and Paul Underwood, Bulk: September 1962 - February 1969July 1955 - October 1977, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-165; 1 folder
        Relates to the fieldwork projects at Saraçhane and Kalenderhane Camii in Istanbul
        Kitzinger, Ernst, 1912-2003
      - Correspondence with Thelma Hammack and John Thacher, August 1955 - November 1961, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-166; 1 folder
        Includes letters between the Turkish Embassy in Washington, D.C. and the Byzantine Institute
      - Correspondence between Paul Underwood and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., John Thacher, Alberta Carpenter), 1955, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-167; 1 folder
        Includes: accounts on riots and the destruction of Greek property in Istanbul in September 1955; financial statements; and the publication of preliminary reports on Kariye Camii
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood and Thelma Hammack, Bulk: May 1966 - May 19681955 - January 1977, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-168; 1 folder
        Includes budgets and financial statements for fieldwork projects at Saraçhane and Kalenderhane Camii in Istanbul, Asinou in Cyprus, and Dibsi Faraj in Syria
      - Correspondence between Paul Underwood and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Thelma Hammack, Ernest Hawkins, and Lawrence Majewski), January - June 1956, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-169; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Relates to the employment of Lawrence Majewski as the Deputy Director and the Byzantine Insitute's interest in establishing a base at Robert College
      - Memoranda, minutes, and reports, January 1956 - January 1962, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-170; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
      - Correspondence with John Thacher, January 1956 - March 1963Bulk: January 1956 - November 1961, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-171; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Includes a newspaper article about Constantine Cavousis
      - Correspondence between Ralph Tuller and John Thacher, January 1956 - December 1963, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-172; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Relates to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute to Dumbarton Oaks
        Ralph Tuller was a lawyer in Boston, Massachusetts
        Tuller, Ralph, 1921-1973
      - Correspondence between Boris Ermoloff and John Thacher, January 1956 - December 1965Bulk: January 1956 - October 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-173; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Relates to the offical transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library to the French government
      - Correspondence between the Holantse Bank in Turkey and John Thacher, January 1956-May 1966Bulk: January 1956 - March 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-174; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Relates to the Turkish bank account for Dumbarton Oaks. Also includes a letter stating the official transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government.
      - Correspondence between Polly Crena de Iongh and John Thacher, February 1956 - September 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-175; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Polly Crena de Iongh was an American violinist, translator, and cultural benefactor. She co-founded W.W. Norton publishing and translated the work of poet Rainer Maria Rilke.
        Crena de Iongh, Polly, 1894-1985
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, April - December 1956, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-176; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
        Relates to fieldwork and admininstrative affairs at Kariye Camii and Fethiye Camii
      - Correspondence between the Houston Friends of the Byzantine Institute and John Thacher, April 1956 - 1963Bulk: 1956 - 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-177; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
      - Correspondence with illustrations from Ernest Hawkins to Paul Underwood, August 31, 1956, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-178; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
      - Applications and work permits for fieldwork projects in Kariye Camii, August 1956 - March 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-179; 1 folder; Box 12 contains correspondence related to the transfer of the Byzantine Institute Library in Paris to the French government and fieldwork, administrative, and financial affairs related to Kariye Camii. Also includes discussions about equipment requirements, work permits, and contributor information.
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, November 1956 - March 1961, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-180; 1 folder
      - Correspondence with the Byzantine Institute (e.g., John Thacher and Thelma Hammack), December 1956 - April 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-181; 1 folder
        Relates to the loan of a Hagia Sophia mosaic reproduction to the Joslyn Art Museum
      - Correspondence between Ercüment Atabay and Paul Underwood, Bulk: 1963-August 19681956 - 1973, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-182/183; 2 folders
        Relates to fieldwork projects at Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. Also includes newspaper clippings about other discoveries in Istanbul.
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and Edward Forbes, January 1957 - July 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-184; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between John Nicholas Brown and John Thacher, January 1957 - December 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-185; 1 folder
        Relates to financial matters, donations, and information on work progress. Includes inquiries on the material from the Red Sea Monastery expeditions and an offprint of Alexandre Piankoff's article "Les Peintures de la Petite Chapelle au Monstère de Saint Antoine".
        Alexandre Piankoff, "Les Paintures de la Petite Chapelle au Monstère de Saint Antoine", Les Cahiers Coptes 12 (1956): 6-16.
      - Correspondence between Charles S. Bird and John Thacher, March 1957 - December 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-186; 1 folder
        Relates to funding and donations
        Charles S. Bird was a supporter of the Byzantine Institute, from East Walpole, Massachusetts
        Bird, Charles S.
      - Correspondence between Byzantine Institute fund contributors and John Thacher, March 1957 - November 1962, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-187; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between the Hegumen of St. Panteleimon Monastery in Mount Athos and John Thacher, August 1957 - April 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-188; 1 folder
        Father Justin was Hegumen of St. Panteleimon Monastery in Mt. Athos, ca. late 1950s
        Justin, Father, St. Panteleimon Monastery
      - Correspondence with the Byzantine Institute (e.g., David Oates, Ernest Hawkins, and Lawrence Majewski), October 1957 - June 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-189; 1 folder
        Relates to considerations and observations on Kariye Camii with drawings by Ernest Hawkins
        Oates, David, 1927-2004
        From David Oates' office, donated by Robert Ousterhout in September 2012.
      - Correspondence with Paul Underwood, Alberta Carpenter, and Thelma Hammack, 1957, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-190; 1 folder
        Includes a copy of Paul Underwood's certificate as the Byzantine Institute Field DIrector
      - Correspondence with the Byzantine Institute (e.g., John Thacher and Thelma Hammack), January 1958 - January 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-191; 1 folder
      - Correspondence with the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Ernest Hawkins, Thelma Hammack, and John Thacher, January 1958 - December 1961, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-192; 1 folder
        Relates to projects in Hagia Sophia, Kariye Camii, and Mount Sinai
      - Correspondence with John Thacher, January 1958 - February 1962, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-193; 1 folder
      - Correspondence with George E. Huenerwadel, Fritz Bilfinger, and Lawrence Majewski, February - March 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-194; 1 folder
        Relates to scaffolding for Hagia Sophia.
        For the drawing referenced in the correspondence, see Oversize: Medium (5th folder:b)
      - Correspondence between John Thacher, Paul Underwood, and Rudolf Naumann, March 1958 - March 1967, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-195; 1 folder
        Relates to the planning of a trial work in Cyprus; the future of the Byzantine Institute's work in Istanbul; and an endeavour to photograph the frescoes of St. Nicholas of Myra by Cyril Mango and Ernest Hawkins
        Rudolf Naumann was a German architectural historian. He was director of the Rome Department of the German Archaeological Institute 1954-1960, and then director of the Istanbul Department of the DAI from 1961 to 1975.
        Naumann, Rudolf, 1910-1996
        Mango, Cyril A., 1928-
      - Correspondence with John Thacher, April 1958 - May 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-196; 1 folder
        Includes information about the Fossati papers in Bellinzona, Switzerland
      - Correspondence between Barclays Bank Limited and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Thelma Hammack), July 1958 - January 1963, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-197; 1 folder
        Includes a grant application submitted by Paul Underwood to the American Philosophical Society
        Barclays Bank Limited, 1690-
      - Correspondence between Archbishop of Mount Sinai and Paul Underwood, September 1958 - September 1963Bulk: September 1958 - August 1960, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-198; 1 folder
        Relates to a plan to repair the mosaics at the Monastery of St. Catherine in Mount Sinai
        Porphyrius III was Archbishop of Mt. Sinai from 1926-1968.
        Porphyrius III, Archbishop of Mount Sinai
      - Mailing List, November 1958, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-199; 1 folder
      - Correspondence between Robert Woods Bliss and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., John Thacher), November 1958 - November 1959, MS.BZ.004-01-01-04-200; 1 folder
    - Correspondence, ca.1960s, MS.BZ.004-01-01-05; 2 boxes including 27 folders
      - Correspondence between Lawrence Majewski and the Byzantine Institute (e.g., Thelma Hammack and John Thacher), January 1959 - March 1967, MS.BZ.004-01-01-05-201; 1 folder
        Relates to the conservation of the floors in Kariye Camii and Fethiye Camii, and the Alexander mosaic portrait in Hagia Sophia